Finding Aid of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Office of the Director Records, 1885-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Office of the Director Records, 1885-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries. Office of the Director
UWM Archival Collection 10
Accession 1998-055
Accession 1999-059
Accession 2005-007
Accession 2006-016
Accession 2006-070
Accession 2007-007
Accession 2009-014
Accession 2009-023
Accession 2009-024
Accession 2010-045
Accession 2011-008
Accession 2011-033
Accession 2012-022
Accession 2012-044
Accession 2013-010
Accession 2015-030
28.6 cubic ft. (49 boxes, including 15 audio reels, 16 audio cassettes, and 23 videocassettes) 1 oversize folder plus additions of 56 cubic ft. (61 boxes), 1 oversize folder, 2693 digital text files, 2 C-type videotapes, and 2 1-inch videotapes
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
The collection contains records of the director of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries and its predecessor institutions, the Library of the Wisconsin State Teachers College, the Kenwood Library, and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Library. The records document the development of automated cataloging and circulation systems at the library. Includes extensive files on the university's Telecommunications Task Force, which made recommendations regarding telecommunications strategy, planning, and acquisitions. The collection also contains records documenting the development of the library's physical plant, the Morris Fromkin Memorial Lecture Series, the Friends of the Library organization and the Staff Association, correspondence with donors of materials, and accession and withdrawal books from the main library of the Normal School and State Teachers College and from specialized libraries. The collection contains little documentation concerning the operations within the library. There are some files concerning the American Geographical Society, Cataloging Department, Technical Services, and the Curriculum Library, and there are miscellaneous annual reports from some of the other departments within the library. Also included are various publications and guides produced by library departments, relating to collections and exhibits.
The university library was formed by the combination of the libraries of the Milwaukee Extension and the Milwaukee State Teachers College after the creation of UWM in 1956. In the early years of the university, the main campus library was the Kenwood Library, housed in what became Mellencamp Hall. As early as 1958, Donald Woods, director of the library, and the Library Committee foresaw the need for expanding the physical facilities of the library and suggested the site of Baker Field House. Although Kenwood Library underwent remodeling in the early 1960s, the need for additional space remained unsolved as the student population of UWM continued to grow. A new library building was planned and constructed in the mid 1960s and the library materials were moved to the new facility in February 1967. Stage II of the library, completed in 1974, and Stage III, completed in 1987, were constructed to provide additional facilities. The library was renamed the Golda Meir Library in 1979. In 2002, the administrative name of the library as a unit was changed to UWM Libraries.
Directors of the Library
1956-1962 Donald Woods (formerly Director of the State Teachers College Library)
1962-1970 Mark Gormley
1971-1989 William Roselle
1990-2003 Peter Watson-Boone
2003-2007 Ewa Barczyk, Interim
2007-2016 Ewa Barczyk
2016- Michael Doylen, Interim
William Moritz served as Interim Director after the administrations of Gormley and Roselle.
The library's mission is to make information available for research in a wide range of fields by undergraduates, graduate students, and faculty. The various departments of the library assist in making the library's holdings accessible. The American Geographical Society, founded in 1851 in New York, moved its library and map collections to the library in 1978. Technical Services is responsible for identifying materials to be added to the library collections and processing these materials for use. The Cataloging Department, a division within Technical Services, has the specific responsibility for classifying and cataloging materials before they are added to the holdings. Interlibrary Loan obtains library materials which are held by other libraries to aid students and faculty in their research. The Archives Department collects and provides reference to materials documenting the activities of UWM. The Milwaukee Area Research Center, created in 1963 by agreement between the Wisconsin Historical Society (WHS) and UWM, provides access to archival and manuscript collections owned by the WHS. The Morris Fromkin Collection, established in 1969, focuses on the quest for social justice in the United States between the end of the Civil War and the end of the New Deal. The Curriculum Library, founded in the early 1950s as part of the State Teachers College, serves the needs of education students.
Other organizations associated with the library include the Friends of the Library and the Staff Association. The Friends of the Library, a group founded to encourage donations to the UWM Library, formed in 1961. In 1964, the group became the Library Associates, and assumed its former name, Friends of the Library, in the 1970s. The group took its current name, Friends of the Golda Meir Library, in 1979. The Staff Association, officially known as the UWM Library Staff Association, appears to have been a continuation of an organization from the State Teachers College since its records predate the establishment of UWM. It is managed by a committee of staff members and conducts social activities for the staff.
The collection contains records of the director of the UWM Libraries and its predecessor institutions, the Library of the Wisconsin State Teachers College, the Kenwood Library, the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Library, and the Golda Meir Library. Most of the records date from 1970 to 1985. The only records predating 1940 are accession and withdrawal books, annual reports, and statistical reports prepared for the American Library Association.
The records largely document the development of automated cataloging and circulation systems at the library. Numerous files throughout the collection pertain to automation. Policy decisions regarding automation planning and implementation can be found in the files of the "Cataloging Department," "Committee on Automated Library Services," "Library Administrative Committee," and "Library Executive Committee." Of particular interest for its detail is the 1973 report, Library Automation at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. The report, by Director William Roselle and Susan Hess, head of library automated operations, was written for the Library Automation Research and Consulting (LARC) Association.
The collection contains little documentation concerning operations within the library. There are some files concerning the American Geographical Society, Cataloging Department, Technical Services, and the Curriculum Library, and miscellaneous annual reports from some of the other departments within the library.
The collection contains extensive files on the university's Telecommunications Task Force, of which William Roselle was chair. The task force, consisting of sixteen campus faculty and administrators appointed in 1982 by Chancellor Frank Horton, examined and described developments and opportunities in the area of telecommunications, and made recommendations regarding telecommunications strategy, planning, and acquisitions for a ten year period. The files contain background materials, meeting agendas and minutes, and reports of the task force.
The development of the physical plant at the UWM Libraries is documented in the files on "Building Data," "Building Program," "Library Administrative Committee," "Library Building Committee," "Library Decorating Committee," "Library Executive Committee," and the "Sculpture in the Library Court."
The files on the Morris Fromkin Memorial Lecture Series include background correspondence, advertising materials including posters, transcripts, some sound recordings, and a videotape of the annual lecture.
The accession books contain the oldest records in the collection, dating to 1885. Most of the books are from the main Library of the Normal School and State Teachers College, but there are some from the specialized libraries as well, including the Parent-Teacher Library, and the Training School Library. The origin of several of the accession books cannot be identified. The collection contains withdrawal books from two specialized libraries, the Elementary Reference Library and the Text-Book Library.
There are numerous files on the Friends of the Library organization and the Staff Association, including by-laws, correspondence, information on their activities, meeting agendas and minutes, membership lists, and newsletters.
Correspondence with donors of materials to the library is incomplete and scattered throughout the collection. Information on major donors can be found under their name; other donors may be located in the records on money gifts and the miscellaneous files.
Newsletters and other publications of the Libraries can be found under their title. The collection also contains a small number of resource guides and exhibition publications, which are listed by short title of the exhibition or by the name of the producing department.
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
UWM Archival Collection 10: Records, 1885-2014
The collection contains a number of additional accessions.
Accession 1998-055: Additions, 1990-1998
Accession 1999-059: Personnel files, closed before 2005
Accession 2005-007: Additions, 1969-2001
Accession 2006-016: Additions, 1982-2000
Accession 2006-070: Administrative Files, 1980-2004
Accession 2007-007: Minutes, 1994-2001
Accession 2009-014: Photographs and Ephemera, 1963-2007
Accession 2009-023: Miscellaneous Files, 1970-1998
Accession 2009-024: Artwork, 2007
Accession 2010-045: Administrative Files, 1991-2008
Accession 2011-008: Administrative Files, 1998-2005
Accession 2011-033: Additions, 1976-1990
Accession 2012-022: Miscellaneous Materials, 1984-2009
Accession 2012-044: Emails, 1997-2003
Accession 2013-010: Tapes, 1979
Accession 2015-030: Fromkin Lecture Series, 1969-2002
Inventories of the personnel files in boxes 23-25 and of accessions 1999-059, 2005-007, 2006-016, and 2006-070 are available in the Archives' case file.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee Buildings Blueprint Collection UWM Archival Collection 50
UW-Milwaukee Photographs Collection UWM Archival Collection 6
UW-Milwaukee Physical Environment Committee Records UWM Archival Collection 120
Administrative/Restriction Information
The unclassified personnel files in boxes 23-25, accession 1999-059, and box 18 of accession 2006-070 are restricted in accordance with UWM Personnel File Policy S-42. Access is regulated by Section III.A.2 and III.A.3.
There are no access restrictions on the rest of the collection, which is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
The provenance of the records is unclear. Many of the records in the collection were created or compiled by the director and various members of the library staff. It is not known if particular records were brought together by the director or if they were separated from other files by library or archives staff. The records, whatever their provenance, were placed together under the library by the Archives Department staff sometime before 1989. When reprocessing began in 1993, it was decided to leave the existing organization intact rather than to possibly confuse the provenance even more. The library transferred another accession (accession 1992-030) in April 1993. Several items from the 1993 Fromkin Lecture were added to the collection in February 1994. Boxes 26-27 (accession 1996-027) were added in March 1997. Accession 1996-040 was transferred in April 1997; accession 1996-047 in May 1997; and accession 2002-029 in May 2002. The Office of the Director transferred a small amount of material to the Archives in August 2008. The Assistant to the Director transferred accession 2008-022 to the Archives in October 2008. Materials transferred piecemeal from the Director's Office in 2008-2010 were retroactively converted to accessions 2008-042, 2009-023, 2009-024, and 2009-050 in March 2010. Linda Kopp transferred accession 1998-055 in January 1998. Dawn Lee-Vue transferred accession 2005-007 in August 2005, accession 2006-070 in June 2007, accession 2007-007 in July 2007, and accession 2011-008 in Aguust 2011. The UWM Libraries transferred accession 2011-033 in January 2012 and accession 2013-010 in August 2013. Accession 2010-045 was transferred by an unknown individual in April 2011. Accession 2012-044 was transferred by an unknown individual in February 2013. Tim Ericson, Assistant Library Director for Archives and Special Collections, transferred accession 2000-037 in January 2000. Michael Doylen transferred accession 2015-030 to the Archives in late 2015.
Contents List
- Records, 1885-2014, UWM Archival Collection 10; 28.6 cubic ft. (49 boxes, including 15 audio reels, 16 audio cassettes, and 23 videocassettes) 1 oversize folder
  - Academic Planning, 1994-1996 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Academic Planning Subcommittee on the Learning Environment, 1995 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Academic Staff Classification and Compensation Plan, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accession Books
    - Vols. 1-3, 1885-1908 (Box 14)
    - Vols. 4-6, 1908-1918 (Box 15)
    - Vols. 7-9, 1918-1929 (Box 16)
    - Vols. 10-12, 1929-1936 (Box 17)
    - Vols. 13-15, 1936-1941 (Box 18)
    - Vols. 16-18, 1941-1945 (Box 19)
    - Unidentified Libraries, 1919-1945, undated (Box 20-21)
  - Acquisitions
    - 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Foreign, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Acquisitions Department, Annual Report, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Activity Summary, 1984-1988 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Academic Titles, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Audio Center, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Manuscripts, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Staff Orientation and Development, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ad Hoc Curriculum Library Committee, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Affairs, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Committee, 1973-1989, Library Administrative Group, Executive Cabinet (Box 40, Folder 1-11)
  - Administrative Data Processing Users Group, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Groups, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Advisory Committee on Educational Technology, 1996-1998 (Box 49, Folder 1-4)
  - Affirmative Action, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1993-1994 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Affirmative Action Report, 1993 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - African-American Librarians Conference Tour, 1994 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - African Program, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Afro American Studies, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Al-Hassan Lecture, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - Alaska, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Allen M. Schlicter Collection of Civil War Materials, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Allocation of Bulk Funds, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - American-Arab Affairs Council Art Exhibit Opening, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  - American Association of Teachers Colleges, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Geographical Society
    - 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1979 February 1, Audio reel (¼ in., 7 ½ ips) (Box 13, Audio 1)
    - Awards, 1998, 1 Videocassette (VHS) (Box 44, Video 1)
    - Bill Roselle, Interview, 1982, 2 Audio cassettes (Box 27, Audio 12-13)
    - Bibliography of Reports and Publications,2001 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Briefing, undated, Audio reel (¼ in., 7 ½ ips) (Box 13, Audio 2)
    - Councilors, 1980-1995 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Dedication, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Megalopolis," 1986 April 30, Audio cassette (Box 27, Audio 8)
    - Program, 1978 August 13, Audio reel (¼ in., 7 ½ ips) (Box 13, Audio 3)
    - Publications, 1966-1990 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - American Indian Week, 1990-1991 (Box 40, Folder 15-16)
  - American Library Association
    - 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Building Committee, 1949-1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Periodical Series, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Revolution Bicentennial Committee, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual Financial Report, 2000-2002 (Box 49, Folder 6-7)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1899-1947 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - 1949-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
    - 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1974-1991 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 40, Folder 17)
  - Applied History Advisory Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books, 1974-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2-9)
  - Arabic Calligraphy, 1988 (Box 40, Folder 18)
  - Architecture of Desire, 1988 (Box 40, Folder 19)
  - Archives
    - 1991-1994 (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - Annual Reports, 1965-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box 47, Folder 1-3)
    - Establishment and Annual Reports, 1969-1986 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Long Range Planning Document, 1983 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Archives Committee, Annual Reports, 1989-1993 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Archives Day, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Archives Publications, 1976-1999, undated (Box 38, Folder 2-3)
  - Area Research Center, 1985-1988 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Arpilles Exhibit and Program, 1985 (Box 40, Folder 21)
  - Art History Accreditation Group, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Art Library Society, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Art of Map Decoration, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 22)
  - Art Work Library, 1989 (Box 40, Folder 23)
  - Arts Program, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Arts Seminar, 1979 (Box 40, Folder 24)
  - Assistant Directors, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Association of College and Research Libraries
    - 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Association of Research Libraries, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Athletic Department, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Audit, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Automated Circulation System, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Automated Operations, 1969-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Automation, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Automation Committee, 1997 (Box 40, Folder 25)
  - Automation Coordinating Committee, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Automation Task Force, 1982-1984 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Bach Birthday Reception, 1985 (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - Baier, Joseph G., Memorial Service, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Baker Geography Lecture, 1987 (Box 40, Folder 27)
  - Base Budget Review Report, 1973-1975 (Box 40, Folder 28)
  - Basquin, Kit, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baum, Werner, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Best, John Collection
    - 1997 (Box 40, Folder 29)
    - 2001 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Beta Phi Mu, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography of Faculty Publications, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Binding Contracts, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bixy Family Donation, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Black Communities, Wisconsin, 1988 (Box 40, Folder 30)
  - Blanket Orders, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Blurbs, 1997 (Box 40, Folder 31)
  - Book Circle, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Book Donations, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Book of Kells, 1990 (Box 40, Folder 32)
  - Book Sale, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 33)
  - Book Signing Event
    - 1992 (Box 40, Folder 34)
    - 1994 (Box 40, Folder 35)
  - Book Theft Detection Systems, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bookplates, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Borowiecki Reception, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 36)
  - Brazilian Program, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Brochure Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Browsing Room, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Brundage, James, 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bryer, Jackson R., 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Budget
    - 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 40, Folder 37)
    - 1966 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 40, Folder 38)
    - 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1985-1991 (Box 28, Folder 4-5)
  - Budget Crisis, 1988 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Budget Planning Document, 1997-1998 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Building Committee, Library Addition, 1970-1974 (Box 40, Folder 39)
  - Building Data, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Building Information, undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Building Plan, 1997 (Box 40, Folder 40)
  - Building Program, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Building Program Materials, 1970-1971 (Box 40, Folder 41)
  - Buildings and Grounds Department, 1957-1967 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Bulgarian Books Exhibit, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Bulletins, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Bute, Mary Ellen Collection and Kit Basquin Correspondence, 1978-1999 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Cable TV, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cain, Stith M., 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Calendar, "Scenes from Lincoln Avenue Circa 1920," 1992-1993 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Campus Police, 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Campus Title Assignment Group, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Canadian Consulate, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Carnegie Grant Accessions, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Cartographic Information Society, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Case Statement Preliminary Draft, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Catalog of Films and Video Tapes, 1971-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Catalogers Meetings, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Cataloging Department
    - 1972-1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Annual Reports, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Binding and Preservation, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Cataloging, 1973-1985 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Cost Studies, 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - CRIN and Barcoding, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Dial Access, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Division for Library Services, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Library Automation, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Management Study of the UWM Library Technical Services Division, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
    - Music Cataloging, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Newsletter, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - OCLC, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Public Catalog, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Celts of Wales, 1980 (Box 40, Folder 42)
  - Center for Research Libraries, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Certificates, 1988 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Chancellor's Office
    - 1983-1990 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Changing of Guard, CSD Program, 1991 (Box 40, Folder 43)
  - Chapman Hall, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Chappelle, Dickey, Program, 1992 (Box 40, Folder 44)
  - Children of World Paint Jerusalem Exhibit, 1980 (Box 40, Folder 45)
  - Chinese Delegation
    - 1985-1986 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - 1991 (Box 40, Folder 46)
  - Chronological Files, 1989-1990 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Circulation Procedures Manual, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Circulation Supervisors, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Civic Center Library, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Civil Service Staff, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Clapp, Verner W., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Clifford Mortimer's Birthday, 2001 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Clodius, Robert L., 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Collection Statistics, 1971-1986 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Collector's Choice: William Morris in Private Press and Limited Editions, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 58)